These people are ghost. Authorities
don't see absolutely anything.
[sighs]
Inside of this bag is $100,000.
What should I spend it on? I could buy a
fancy orange jacket. I could buy a new
drone. I could buy like really nice
antique maps. But actually, I can't
spend [music] this money cuz I have a
big problem. This money is dirty.
No, not like germs. I mean, I'm sure
there's plenty of those, but it's a
different kind of dirty. This money is
dirty because I got it from selling
drugs.
And in fact, I can't spend it because I
need to get it back to my bosses in
another country.
I could take it to a bank and deposit
it, but they'll end up asking questions
and report it to the government.
I could try to ship it, bring it with me
on a flight, but that also can get
pretty risky.
Ultimately, I need to clean this money
to launder it. It's not going to be
easy, though.
Okay. No, I did not sell drugs to get
this money. And no, it is not dirty. And
in fact, it's not even real.
[music]
But we'll leave it here to remind us
what money looks like. Because a lot of
money that moves around our world is
dirty.
More than $50 million in drug cash
vanish from US streets without tripping
a single bank alarm. And this was just
one city. Multiply this around the world
and you can see how much money is
flowing around. I mean we're talking,
you know, trillions and trillions of
dollars. Roughly [music]
3 to 5% of world GDP is the proceeds of
crime. That [music] equates to roughly
$4 trillion.
>> Drugs, human trafficking, weapons,
illegal wildlife parts. It all needs
money to work. [music]
>> Criminals, criminal organizations commit
crime for what? For money. [music]
Money.
>> And if I were in this hypothetical
scenario, I actually have another
option. an option that will allow me to
move my money without any government or
law enforcement knowing. It is called
flying money. [music]
It's a mostly invisible system. It
secretly connects the whole world of
organized crime and helps to fund it.
Connecting illegal gold mines in Congo
to the cocaine trade to weapons to the
illegal trade of organs which is
connected to illegal timber and tusk
poaching and shark fins and jaguar bone
wine. All of this somehow linked to
unassuming places like a restaurant in
Lima, Peru or a clothing store in Rome.
It's all connected, but it's almost
impossible to see.
The money doesn't move. It flies,
[music] right? It's kind of a ghost, so
you can't trace it.
>> These people are ghosts flying 30,000 ft
around us.
>> That's Andrea Costa. He actually came to
us and pitched me on this story because
he's spent years infiltrating this
system. He and his team have been
risking their lives to see how this
actually works to try to find solutions.
So thanks to Andrea and his team and
many others. We have this story and
we're starting to understand it. And I
want to show it to you how it works,
[music] what it enables, and what we
might do about it.
I'm in Taiwan right now working on my
next story. But I want to quickly tell
you about the sponsor of today's video,
which is something I actually use quite
a bit. We are currently engaged in a
very crazy time where your data, your
name, your address, your birthday, your
viewing habits. This stuff is bought and
sold on an open market. It's valuable
stuff and there's sort of a shadowy
invisible market that no one wants you
to know about that takes this
information and sells it to people who
want to sell you stuff or put you on
people's search sites or jack up your
insurance premiums. Incogn is the answer
to this. Cogni is a service that you
give the permission to go off and start
making requests to take you off these
lists. You don't really have to do
anything. You just get to sit in the
background and on their fancy dashboard,
you can just track the progress, how
many lists have been requested that you
may be taken off of, which have been
successful. A feature I really like is
this custom removal feature, which
allows you to send a specific site or
register that your name is on. Someone
at Incogn then handles this for you.
They go after this site and make sure
that your name is taken off. I've been
tracking over the years. They've taken
my name off over a thousand of these
data broker lists, which is a very
satisfying thing. I sleep better at
night knowing that I have a little bit
more privacy. Incogn.
It's incogn.com/jnyh
harris. You get 60% off the unlimited
plan. The unlimited plan ensures that
every month incogn is searching for my
name and my information and making
requests to get me off these lists. It's
made a big difference in my life. I am a
big fan. Grateful that they sponsor this
channel. Again, it's incogn.com/jny
harris. Go get 60% off and reclaim your
privacy. Today, I'm working on this
incredible video from Taiwan. There's
claw machines and arcades everywhere.
This is an amazing country. Let's get
back to this story about flying money.
>> So, it goes back to the Tang Dynasty.
This is one of the golden ages of
China's history. The capital is huge.
It's one of the most populous cities in
the world and it's thriving. People are
using money in the form of copper coins.
Let's say I'm a businessman who sells
tea. I live up here and I routinely go
to the capital to sell my harvest. I
sell it off to the nobles and the elites
and the tea drinkers of the capital and
I get paid in copper coins. Uh-oh. These
coins are not light. This is going to be
hard to bring all these coins back up to
my home region. And I'm going to be
vulnerable to robbers as I go along my
journey.
So, let's do this. I'll take my bag of
coins to a merchant. And he'll give me a
little piece of paper. And he'll tell me
that once I'm back home, I should go see
his merchant friend and give him [music]
this piece of paper. This light, easy to
carry piece of paper. Nice. Once I'm
home, I take that paper to the merchant
that the guy from the capital knows. And
because these two are trusted partners,
the merchant in my hometown [music]
honors it and gives me a bag of copper
coins that's the exact same amount as
what I gave his friend back in the
capital. The relationship between these
two, I don't totally know. They'll
settle up later. All I care about is I
got paid my copper coins and I didn't
have to carry them from the capital.
This is magic built on trust. In fact,
this was flying money.
[music]
>> Flying money is actually thought to be
the first form of paper money.
>> Now, China and the Tang Dynasty were not
the only people to come up with this.
They were one of the earlier and one of
the more widespread, but other cultures
settled on these mirror transactions as
a way to transfer value without having
to carry a bunch of money or gold a long
distance.
We're talking about the Chinese version
here because this would go on to inform
a global network that we see today. As
tens of millions of Chinese immigrants
spread throughout the world, they were
often persecuted, segregated, and
excluded. They stayed tight-knit,
[music] Chinatowns became not only a
cultural refuge, but also commercial
hubs that were anchored by family
association, clan networks with strong
cultural ties maintained with the
homeland, with mainland China. These
communities are built off of some strong
core [music] values. Self-reliance,
mutually beneficial relationships that
are based on trust, reciprocity, [music]
and personal bonds, and often a very
strong work ethic and business sense.
Making money with often cashbased
[music] businesses, sending a lot of
that money to family around the world.
But soon this global diaspora network
[music] of trust and connection would be
abused by criminals who would use it to
wash dirty money. Using this to create a
shadow banking system that was near
impossible for outsiders to understand
or infiltrate.
[music]
So let me show you how this works today.
how those same concepts that we saw in
the Tang Dynasty play out in a real
world scenario today.
>> Wealthy Chinese individuals are using
flying money to get their money out of
China. Any change in the polit bureau or
any change in the kind of rulings or
legal system could have your money taken
off you at any time. [music]
So, let's say there's a man in China
named Mr. Chen. He's very rich. He's got
a lot of extra money and he wants to
invest his money elsewhere. got $2
million extra dollars that maybe he
wants to buy a luxury apartment in Miami
with. He has a cousin in the US who
could help him. But he's got a problem.
>> In 2017, the Chinese government
implemented a $50,000 limit on the
amount of money that you could get out
of China.
>> This is a way for the Chinese government
to stop tons of money [music] from
flowing out of the country. Now, that's
not going to stop anyone. So, they turn
to the underground banks. So, Mr. Chen
goes to a broker in China and he pays
him the $2 million. He does this from
one Chinese bank account to another,
maybe in a series [music] of small
transactions so he doesn't draw too much
attention. And reminder, this isn't
dirty money. Mr. Chen just makes a lot
of money in his job and wants to invest
it elsewhere. He didn't get it from like
drugs or anything. Okay, so anyway, the
broker tells Mr. Chen to tell his cousin
in the US to go to a shop in Chicago and
ask for the broker's trusted contact,
who's another broker in the United
States, and to give him a special code.
Meanwhile, here in the United States,
there's something else going on. There's
a drug dealer from a Mexican drug
cartel. He has his own financial puzzle
[music] to solve, and it has nothing to
do with Mr. Chen yet. He's been selling
drugs on the street of Chicago, and now
he has $2 million in cash. Now, this
cash is definitely dirty. It's the
definition of dirty money. Has no paper
trail from where it came from. Just a
huge amount of cash from drugs. He needs
to somehow make this money look
legitimate [music]
and get it back to his cartel bosses in
Mexico. And these days, it's not easy to
do that. So, he goes to this same
Chinese broker in the United States, the
same guy that Mr. Chen told his cousin
to go to, and he gives him this $2
million saying, "I need this to get to
my bosses back in Mexico." So, this
broker now owes the cartel $2 million.
And this maybe goes without saying,
these are all simplified numbers and
[music] examples to show the concept.
Okay, this is where these two start
communicating. These two brokers,
>> they know each other. They're probably a
member of the same extended family,
clan, tribe. They're not going to take
advantage of each other.
>> They're talking over an encrypted
communication app. And the broker in
China tells the broker in the United
States that Mr. Chen's cousin is coming
and that he will give him a special
code. And when he does, give him $2
million. The cousin arrives at the
broker shop, gives him the code, and in
exchange, he gives the cousin $2
million. The $2 million, in fact, that
he got from the drug dealer. That cousin
then deposits into a variety of family
business accounts under a bunch of
different names so he doesn't raise any
flags. And eventually he uses that money
to buy a luxury apartment in Miami for
his cousin. So look, Mr. Chen now has a
$2 million asset and he didn't have to
send any money across any borders or
through any financial system. His $2
million stayed in China and the $2
million used for his apartment stayed in
the United States.
Okay, but look, there's still some
imbalance here. There's still people who
owe each other money. The broker in
China still has that $2 million that Mr.
Chen gave him. And the cartel in Mexico
still needs to get their $2 million of
drug money. And this is when they turn
to the global economy. [music]
When they want to settle up accounts,
often times they go back and settle
accounts through trade. Traditional,
historically, and culturally, that's
what they did. We always talk about
following the money. Sometimes it's more
important to follow the value. By the
way, that's John Casara who is a former
US intelligence officer. He was a
special agent for the Treasury where he
spent decades investigating these types
of crimes. He now writes books. He's
very helpful for this story. Okay, so it
turns out that the broker in China has a
company, a legal, legitimate looking
company. He sells kitchen appliances
that are made in China. And this is a
perfect cover for what he's about to do
next because the cartel in Mexico also
has a front company where they sell
kitchen appliances in a retail store in
Mexico. Okay, now watch this clever move
between these two. The cartel purchases
$10 million of refrigerators from the
Chinese broker's appliance company. But
instead of charging $10 million, the
broker only charges $8 million. And on
the invoices, they just put these are $8
million worth of refrigerators. $2
million is secretly transferred
illegally in this legal looking trade
transaction that flows through the
global economy. These appliances roll
into port. They're transferred to the
retail floor. [music] They're sold. And
look, everyone in this little
transaction is settled. And the
authorities have no idea. How could
they? because most of this transaction
left no paper trail. The ledger is only
trust
and let me just re-emphasize that this
is not just a Chinese diaspora thing.
This kind of informal trustbased value
transfer has been used by many different
groups and networks around the world.
Hala is in effect the de facto banking
system of Afghanistan. All eyes are on
hala in the Middle East and terrorism
[music] coming out of that part of the
world. From terrorists using it to fund
attacks to allowing the Italian mafia to
have a global footprint, this is a very
common way of transferring and
laundering money. But flying money,
specifically this Chinese diaspora
network in many different countries is
much bigger than all of those other
networks.
Hey, real quick, a little behind the
scenes thing that I want to tell you
about. This video that you're watching
right now has been available for people
to watch early and adree over on our new
platform, New Press. New Press is the
place where anyone for free can come
contribute to our journalism, make it
better. It's also a place where you can
support the work that we're doing here.
And for those who do support, you get
access to our videos early and ad free.
So, if you want to support us or just
contribute to our journalism for free,
head to New Press to sign up to check it
out. We're building a community of
curious people over there. And if you
like this video, you might like what's
going on over there. Okay, let's keep
going. So, if this is so hard to track
and infiltrate and see, how do we even
know any of this? And the answer is the
hard work and risktaking of
investigators like the ones we've been
talking to.
>> It's very hard to break into for law
enforcement. Any investigator in
financial crimes investigator worth
their salt will tell you that it's human
source information that makes the best
cases. AI by itself is not going to make
a case to infiltrate this network. You
need uh you need time. You need to get
their trust. You need to use certain
kind of undercover operatives. Andrea
told me that when he got into this 13
years ago, he had no idea that he would
end up investigating moneyaundering and
shadow banking
>> in Kenya working as a security and
geopolitical consultant and it was right
in the middle of the elephant poaching
crisis when we were losing 40 50,000
elephants per year for the ivory trade.
We definitely needed a change of
strategy, new ideas. So I resigned to
create the first intelligence agency for
Earth, a sort of CIA for for the
environment. And so I started recruiting
former FBI, former CIA, crime analyst,
undercover specialist. Andrea quickly
realized that environmental crimes like
poaching are not just their own thing.
They operate in the same networks and
systems as seemingly unrelated crimes.
trafficking, wildlife, illegal fishing,
illegal locking, legal gold mining,
money laundering, human smuggling, human
trafficking, drug trafficking, weapons
trafficking, and so forth.
>> And even though we live in a world of
electronic money and surveillance and
AI, the reality is this system, it's
built off of old school methods. And so
the only way to infiltrate it is through
human intelligence. [music] You have to
physically meet and be friend with the
very guy who is doing that. That's
classic human intelligence from the old
generations of of spies and intelligence
officers. You need Chinese-speaking
undercover operatives. These are a rare
commodity. I'm telling you, it's really
really difficult to find them and train
them and trust them. undercover missions
uh in all continents infiltrating dozens
and dozens of organized crime groups and
trafficking groups. We are usually able
to film and record every meeting we have
with these people. So, we have tons of
[music] intelligence coming from these
recordings, sending some people to jail,
putting together an incredible amount of
intelligence about how these groups
operate. [music] We regularly produce
intelligence reports for law enforcement
agencies. They received a lot of
information from us about the [music]
most important members of this network
with profiles and everything.
[music]
>> Andrea gave us some of his undercover
footage showing these flying money
networks in action.
>> Truly the most [music] important and
revealing undercover operation in over
10 years of work in the field.
>> This is shot by two of his undercover
operators who have spent months getting
close to this one guy. He's a trafficker
from China. He's living in Mexico and
he's a big player in the illegal seafood
trade. And these undercover operators
are posing [music] as businessmen
interested in putting money into the
illegal seafood trade. With time, these
undercover operators successfully
[music]
earn his trust. And he agrees to
introduce them to other people in his
network, trusted partners in the
trafficking ring. 2 days later, the same
two undercover operators meet one of
these contacts in a Starbucks in Mexico
City. This guy's also from China and
focuses on trafficking [music]
product and money between Mexico and the
US, but not just for seafood. [music]
It's also revealed that he traffics
people and uses mirror transaction to
clean huge amounts of money for the
cartels in Mexico.
>> The undercover operators are getting
deeper and deeper into this ring. And
soon they're being offered an
introduction to a corrupt customs and
immigration officer at the Mexico City
airport. someone who helps clear illegal
products coming in and out of the
country. They go to dinner for this
meeting and the customs officer shows
them his badge. During the dinner, the
corrupt customs officer leaves the table
and they start speaking Chinese. This
original trafficker telling the
undercover operatives just how valuable
this customs contact is.
[music]
While the customs officer [music] is
gone, the undercover operators try to
get a glimpse of his notebook. He
returns and the conversation turns to
cash. What techniques they use to hide
huge amounts of cash when it's going in
and out of the airport.
This special dye makes the cash
completely invisible to airport scanning
equipment.
Yes, I do.
>> You can see how difficult but useful
this kind of human intelligence is.
>> The level of insight and understanding
of [music] how these networks operate is
unprecedented.
>> But what this also reveals is how what
originally looked like someone
trafficking seafood is something much
bigger.
This Chinese traffickers and money
launderers were at [music] the center of
all sorts of crimes.
>> But this was confusing to me. When
Andrea originally approached me, I
didn't understand this concept, how
wildlife poaching could be deeply
interconnected with the drug trade.
[music]
Okay, [music] another example. Let's
start here. The Sinoaoa cartel is in
northern Mexico and they've gotten into
the fishing business, hiring local
fishermen to go after valuable products
like shark fins, which can sell for up
to $630 a piece. Seahorses, which end up
in jars like this to make wine, sea
cucumbers, abalone. But most valuable of
all are these.
They call this the cocaine of the sea,
the swim bladder of a fish called toaba.
Now, this is a highly endangered fish
whose bladder, despite having no proven
health benefits, is highly valued in
traditional [music] Chinese medicine.
But more importantly, they are a modern
status symbol in China. And the reason
this is called the cocaine of the sea is
because it sells for tens of thousands
of dollars a kilogram.
So, the cartel is going after this
stuff. And let's say they harvest $6
million worth of illegal seafood
products, including these very expensive
fish platters. This is not dirty cash,
it's dirty product, though. And in order
to get across the borders, they go also
to a broker, a Chinese broker in Mexico.
So, they coordinate the smuggling of,
let's say, half of this product, $3
million worth to China. Maybe this would
be bribing a shipping company not to
inspect the shipment. Or maybe they'll
just carry these fish bladders in their
luggage on a flight back to China. Maybe
they'll hide them in legal products like
roof tiles or other fish products. One
way or another, they get to China.
[music]
Once there, the Chinese mafia takes it
and sells it in their own market to the
rich. They make their money back.
Probably they get some profit, but
again, for our simple math, let's just
keep this at $3 million. They have $3
million extra dollars, but they haven't
paid for the product yet. They haven't
paid the cartel. To pay the cartel back,
they're once again going to turn to the
global economy. This time, they're going
to sell a chemical, phenthyl bromide,
which is actually a legitimate
pharmaceutical for like farming
chemicals, but it's also a key
ingredient to make fentinol. They'll
doctor the invoices once again, and
value has been exchanged, and these two
are now settled with no money being
exchanged for the illegal marine
products. [music]
Okay, but remember there's a second half
to this. The other $3 million gets
smuggled into the United States where a
Chinese broker receives the products and
sells them to rich Chinese consumers
there. [music] This US broker in the
United States is now in possession of $3
million of dirty money. And the only
thing that has crossed any borders into
the United States are these illegal
seafood products. At the same time,
let's say that the cartel in the United
States has also amassed another $10
million in drug money, drug sales,
[music] and they need to clean that
money and get it back to Mexico. So,
they bring that cash to the same Chinese
broker who now has $13 million of dirty
money. Three from the sea products, 10
from the drug cash. And all of that is
owed to the cartel in Mexico. And here
comes the trust that makes flying money
work. These two Chinese brokers know
each other. They do business together.
They're constantly in communication on a
encrypted platform like WeChat. And they
want to keep the cartel happy. So the
Chinese broker in the US asks the
Chinese broker in Mexico to just quickly
pay $13 million of their own to the
cartel in pesos. The cartel is now made
whole for all of the fish bladder and
the $10 million of dirty cash. And yet
the Chinese broker up in the United
States is still sitting on $13 million
of dirty money that they need to clean.
They also need to somehow repay their
trusted broker in Mexico. So, how will
they do this? [music]
Well, as we're seeing, they've got a
couple options here, but one that is
becoming more and more common is to just
cheat the global economy.
This broker in the US runs an electronic
store. This is their front for their
real business. And to make this all
work, this broker puts in an order for
$14 million worth of electronics from a
company in China that, [music] you
guessed it, is actually a front for the
Chinese mafia. The mafia sources and
ships off these electronics to the US in
an official legal looking $14 million
transaction for electronics. It's on its
way to the United States. But actually,
if anyone were to look and evaluate what
is inside of these shipping containers,
they would see a bunch of cheap
electronics worth probably only $1
million. A bunch of knockoff watches and
[music] cameras and tablets. The broker
receives those electronics and puts them
for sale in their store. You've maybe
been into a store where stuff like this
is being sold. All of this helps drive
the perception that this is a legitimate
business. But really, this whole
transaction was purely meant to transfer
$13 million to the Chinese [music] mafia
in this complex deal involving marine
wildlife, drugs, and a bunch of money
that is now clean because it flowed
through a legitimate looking
transaction. [music]
And there are so many more forms that
this can take. Value transfer. Maybe the
mafia in China will hire the cartel to
smuggle Chinese immigrants into Mexico
and then across the border into the
United States. That's a lucrative human
trafficking effort that both groups make
a lot of money off of. The cartel could
extract even more value from the
transaction by enlisting these migrants
to carry drugs for them into the United
States.
[music]
>> [bell]
>> So, these are simplified examples, but
they're based off [music] of realworld
cases that have been revealed by these
investigations from people like Andrea
and his team. Within these transactions,
[music]
there's a lot more nuance. All the
brokers are taking commission. There are
bribes usually for officials to look the
other way. The complexity of the ledgers
[music] much more than what we've laid
out here. And when you start to go into
these investigations, you see the
attempt of the investigators to like
piece together [music] some of these
networks, all the different nodes in
just one country or one community, and
they very quickly become too complex to
follow. They get dizzying really fast.
[bell]
And by the way, we've been focusing on
this triangle, China, United States,
Mexico. It's a very common one here, but
this system is global. [music]
It moves money all around the world. It
allows the Italian mafia to offload
their illgotten cash to a Chinese broker
in Rome, who then might buy luxury cars
for a Russian oligarch, helping them
evade taxes or sanctions and being part
of other mere transactions in China and
elsewhere. [music] Transactions that
deal in rubles and euros and Chinese
yuan, all evading official transactions
or taxes. That same broker might be
approached again by the mafia who just
received a cocaine shipment from
Colombia. They need to pay the cartel $5
million in drug money. So they give them
a duffel bag full of $5 million in the
form of euros. And this broker gets on
WeChat and messages a longtime friend
[music]
running a restaurant in Colombia telling
them to release that same amount in
local currency to the cartel. the money
is transferred and these two will settle
up in some transaction in the future.
Maybe a series of WeChat transactions
[music] or messing with trade invoices
as we've seen. So you can see this
network touches everything [music] and
it links casinos in Myanmar to
struggling fishermen in Peru and Jaguar
fangs to illegal gold mining, crypto
scams and [music] unassuming electronic
stores in New York City, illegal timber
and human trafficking and shark fins,
gold bars in Dubai and meth labs [music]
and seahorses and rhino horns. Cocaine
and ivory and luxury apartments in
Vancouver and border tunnels. [music]
Flying money is one shadow banking
network that could touch all of it.
[music]
As I've made abundantly clear, fighting
this is hard and in part because of how
low tech it is.
>> Back in the day, it was much easier for
law enforcement to tap into people and
listen to people. They know that the
more they stay away from anything
digital or computer related, the the
better it is and the safer it is.
>> And yet, we're entering an era of
encryption and decentralized currency,
which are two very powerful technologies
[music]
to enable and improve a system like
this.
>> You have flying money pair with crypto
pair with the encrypted communication.
the system is almost unbreakable [music]
from the outside.
>> If there's one thing I feel in looking
at this is that like there are people
who are taking this seriously working on
this trying to [music] infiltrate these
systems and in fact governments are
getting on board and getting savvy to
how serious of an issue this is.
>> US Congress and and even the EU
parliament now threat Chinese money loan
organization as priority threats. The
Chinese government itself is recognizing
that this is a big problem and assessing
ways to [music] crack down on it.
But these are small dents in a very huge
problem.
>> $4 trillion of illicit proceeds every
year that impacts everybody. Honestly,
we have the laws, the rules, the
regulations we need. Now, what these
experts stress is that the real key to
enforcement is actually dedicating
enough actual humans and funding, most
importantly, enough patience to
investigate and infiltrate these
networks.
>> If I was a government agency, I would
put together a task force and start
laundering and moving money around the
world with them. That's what I call the
last mile. What we as an NGO cannot do.
Law enforcement is rated and rewarded
because of statistics. But in [music]
order to make this work, we have to
change the incentives for law
enforcement. We have ICE, immigration,
and customs enforcement. They'll go
after the quick border stats. All the
resources are going into immigration
instead of going after these long-term
complex meaningful moneyaundering cases.
Criminals are motivated by money and
once they have the money they have to
launder it. Whether it be the fentanyl,
whether it be human trafficking that
occurs in the strip malls across this
country, a romance scam, an investment
scam, somebody trying to fleece you out
of your hard-earned money that affects
everybody. [music]
Heat. Heat.
[music]
>> [music]